Guide to the Don Hobart Collection 1960-1971
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Don Hobart Collection
1960-1971
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
HOBA
Don Hobart
331 reels
The collection includes 52 episodes of Hobart’s wildlife series “High & Wild,” 26 episodes of his series “Wild World of People,” and 28 additional films.
Moving Images Collection
Donald (Don) Bruce Hobart was born in Hell Canyon country in November 6, 1918. He later moved to Spokane, WA with his parents.
December 8, 1941, the day after Pearl Harbor was bombed by the Japanese, Hobart enlisted in the Army Air Corps. He flew P-40s and P-51s as part of the Flying Tigers in China, earning a Purple Heart among other medals. He was shot down and hiked 300 miles to safety in 32 days with the help of the Chinese underground.
After the war, Hobart joined the fire department and owned an archery shop in St. John, Oregon. He married Delores “Dot” Andrews in 1943; they were together for 56 years before she died in a traffic accident in 1998. Hobart had three children: Michael, born in 1945; Patricia, 1947; and Douglas, 1948.
Partnering with Rudy Lachenmeir, owner of Fishing and Hunting News, during the 1950s, Hobart travelled around Oregon shooting and narrating films for KGW.
In the 1960s, Hobart started his own film company, launching with two full-length feature films focusing on Alaskan wildlife. These films evolved into his series “High and Wild.” “High and Wild” was amongst the first outdoor shows to air, starting on Portland’s KGW (8) and later on KPTV (12). Episodes primarily covered Oregon, Washington, Alaska, California, Idaho, and Montana as well as parts of Canada including British Columbia.
Hobart’s subsequent series “Wild World of People” focused on the much the same region of “High and Wild” but with a focus on the unique people and events within the area, often using materials initially shot during “High and Wild.” Footage from “Wild World of People” was bought by the producers of the national show “Real People” who then incorporated some of its footage.
Hobart spent his later life living with his son Doug and daughter-in-law Sue in Scappoose, OR. Hobart died March 19, 2012, at age 95.
The collection includes 52 episodes of Hobart’s wildlife series “High & Wild” and 26 episodes of his series “Wild World of People” focusing on people and event in the Pacific Northwest, Alaska, and Canada. The collection also include films such as “Hood River Story,” “Wemme Fire Test,” “Trout Unlimited,” and “The Way to the Top,” focusing on skiing at Timberline Lodge. Other gems include a safety and education film "Prudence en Motoneige" ("Caution in Snowmobiling"), a commercial how-to for snow tires, hikes of the Gifford Pinchot National Forest, frontier reenactments and shooting contests, demolition explosions, a wedding home video, Alaskan hunting trips, man-made forest brush burning, and reels of fish and wildlife adventures. Each can series may include prints, A/B rolls, inter/neg, and/or opt/neg tracks.
Series A: High & Wild, 1960-1971
Series B: Wild World of People, 1960-1971
Series C: Don Hobart Others & Unknowns
The collection is open to the public.
Donated by Don Hobart’s son Douglas Hobart after his father’s death.
Show descriptions donated along with film reels are stored at the Moving Images Collection.
Don Hobart Collection, HOBA, Oregon Historical Society, Moving Images Collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Hobart, Donald--Archives; Hobart, Don
Alaska; British Columbia; California; Canada; Idaho; Montana; Oregon; Pacific Northwest; Washington
Fishing; Hunting; Outdoor Sports; Racing; Rafting; Snowmobiles; Wildlife
{l}
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series A: High & Wild, 1960-1971
  - H&W01 Snake River Sturgeon: A sturgeon fishing trip into the rugged Hell's Canyon of the Snake River, between Idaho and Oregon, shows a woman taking a 5'10" giant white sturgeon on light tackle, probably the biggest fish she will ever catch in fresh water. Has thrilling underwater shots. (07348)
  - H&W02 Wallowa Mountain Deer Hunt: Don Hobart leads a four man party on a 20 mile pack trip and gets a big buck deer. Magnificent eastern Oregon scenery. (07349)
  - H&W03 Oregon Gold Fever…Then and Now: Don Hobart's how-to pan gold tour of gold mines opened around 1900 reminds us of the rich and exciting heritage of "the land of the Golden West." (07350)
  - H&W04 Odell Lake Mackinaw: High in the Cascades, the Hobart crew casts deep in Odell Lake to tempt those furious fighters, the Mackinaw trout. (07351)
  - H&W05 Victoria, BC Octopus Hunt: Don Hobart's cameras take you along to help capture dangerous marine animals for Victoria's underwater gardens. Spectacular British Columbia coastal scenery and underwater shots. (07352)
  - H&W06 Paulina Rodeo: All the whoop-hollering excitement of one of Oregon's most competitive rodeos. One young rider misses a fatal kick by just inches, but walks away from his fall without even losing his hat. (07353)
  - H&W07 Timberline Ski Story: See slow motion classic skiing from the 10,000 foot level down to world-famous Timberline Lodge on the beautiful south face of Mount Hood. Exciting jumps and magnificent sunsets. (07354)
  - H&W08 Baker Elk Hunt: Watch an all-action elk hunt from the moment the hunters don snow shoes and skis until you see the kill from over a hunter's shoulder. (07355)
  - H&W09 Alaska Mishaps: A behind-the-scenes look at a Hobart camera trip in Alaska, including a heart-in-throat airplane accident, but nobody gets hurt. (07356)
  - H&W10 Winter Steelhead Fishing: See fishermen with the fever - Steelhead fever - at work in two very different stream; the short coastal Nestucca and the Washougal, a tributary of the Columbia. Terrific coastal scenery. [no print] (07357)
  - H&W11 Nehalem Bay Story: The beautiful Pacific Ocean provides fun and food as the High & Wild camera crew takes you on a family outing for clams, crabs, and spectacular salmon fishing on the Oregon Coast. (07358)
  - H&W12 Eastern Oregon Ringnecks: Fly with the Hobart crew to Vale, Oregon for fabulous pheasant shooting. See a kill in slow motion from over the hunter's shoulder and the perfect performance of two well-trained bird dogs. (07359)
  - H&W13 Snake River Steelhead: The mystery and excitement of challenging steelhead fishing in the Snake River, Hell's Canyon at the mouth of the Salmon River, where the Hobart crew gets 15 to 20 pound steelheads. [no print] (07360)
  - H&W14 Deschutes River Drift: An exciting 45 mile drift in a rubber life raft through the white water of the Deschutes River. See rattle snakes, wildlife and the wild rapids of this famous stream. (07361)
  - H&W15 Indian Wild Horse Round-Up: The camera follows an unusual Indian girl on her duties of fire-warden, rach boss, and all-around cowgirl. A roaring range fire, wild horse round-up and branding session [with] Zelam Smith, the charming, capable Indian girl. [no print] (07362)
  - H&W16 Canadian Wildlife: Don Hobart's camera searches out and records the autumn madness of the elk and the Rocky Mountain Bighorn sheep during the rutting season. Close-up of two bull elk in an all-out fight for each other's harem. (07363)
  - H&W17 Bonneville Sturgeon: High & Wild camera follows four noisy, exuberant fisherman as they fish the waters of the mighty Columbia, below Bonneville Dam, for the giant white sturgeon. Camera shows how and where these heavy-weight fish are caught. (07364)
  - H&W18 Alaska Bush Pilot: Don Hobart's camera looks over the shoulder of a bush pilot as he makes his dangerous take-offs and landings on the steep mountain sides and rocky river bars. Emergency reconstruction and fly-out of a badly wrecked plane from the wilds of interior Alaska. (07365)
  - H&W19 Mountain Climbing School: High & Wild camera joins a group of novice mountains climbers as their instructors guide them through the risky but breath-taking techniques of climbing. Swift rope descents, climbing of vertical rock walls and use of equipment. (07366)
  - H&W20 Florence Story: The cameraman follows a Bass fisherman on Siltcoose Lake. He takes 6 Bass in 6 casts and not one fish is under 3 pounds. The Dune Buggies ride in the sand dunes and the cameraman takes a close look at the sea lions from the Sea Lion Caves. [no print] (07367)
  - H&W21 Diamond Lake Rainbows: Spring fishing trip into high Cascade Mountains. Rainbow trout fishing, like fishermen dream about, with fighting trout measuring generally over 15 inches. (07368)
  - H&W22 Rockhound Pow Wow: Camera covers the strangely fascinating hobby, which ranks second in the world of rock hunting. Annual get-togethers of thousands of rockhounds from all over the country. (07369)
  - H&W23 Canadian Ski Safari: We [High & Wild] take a trip to three new British Columbia ski areas and find fresh powdered snow with steep slopes and an amazing lack of skiers. Our host is the Canadian trainer for Canada's Winter Olympic Ski Team. [no print] (07370)
  - H&W24 Nate Buell, Trout Fisherman: The camera follows three top fisherman on a fishing safari to their favorite streams and lakes. A variety of fishing techniques and amazing results are recorded. [no print] (07371)
  - H&W25 Eddy Martin's White Sheep Hunt: The High & Wild cameras go to Alaska for this adventure. An eleven year old boy bags a world-record-class Dall Ram on his first big game hunt. [no print] (07372)
  - H&W26 McKenzie White River Parade: The annual White River Parade with fun for all. Don Hobart's camera records the spills and chills of one the zaniest float trips ever recorded. (07373)
  - H&W27 People of Point Hope: Film story of the daily lives of the Eskimo families of Point Hope, Alaska, 150 miles above the Arctic Circle. (07374)
  - H&W28 Elisha Rock, Seal Hunter: Cameras go out on the ice by dog team and follow Eskimo seal hunter [Bill Ellis] in his search for food on the open ice of the Arctic Ocean. [no print] (07375)
  - H&W29 Polar Bear Hunt: A hunt of the Giant White Bear of the North. The cameras follow the guide and hunter [Ed McCans] right down to the kill. [no print] (07376)
  - H&W30 Jolly 'Copters: The cameras show the building and flying of a one [person] 'copter costing less than $500. [OHS Add: one-person gyro-copter builders Chuck Bannock, Al Cole, and Dale Gordon.] (07377)
  - H&W31 Feather River Run: Placed in the Feather River country of northern California, the cameras record the Kayak races through the wild white water. (07378)
  - H&W32 The Wild Owyhee: A five day drift trip down the Owyhee River from Rome, Oregon, to the Owyhee Reservoir, a distance of 50 miles through spectacular canyons. (07379)
  - H&W33 Wilderness Survival: This show records the abilities of men to survive under wilderness conditions, filmed with the cooperation of the USAF [US Air Force] in the High Cascades. (07380)
  - H&W34 Canadian Lake Trout: A fishing trip to Cunningham Lake in northern British Columbia for trout weighing up to 25 pounds. Spectacular fishing. [no print] (07381)
  - H&W35 The Whitehorse Rendezvous: Winter celebration at Whitehorse, Canada that includes dog racing and other events that hark back to the days of the gold prospectors and trappers of the north. (07382)
  - H&W36 Mount Bachelor Ski Adventure: Spectacular skiing at Mt. Bachelor, Oregon, includes the Junior National Ski Championships and other events. [no print] (07383)
  - H&W37 Banks Iron Horse: The small town of Banks [in Oregon] holds an annual barbecue and get-together that includes [a] 25 mile mountain ride on a 1906 train, plus special civil war cannon show. (07384)
  - H&W38 Coastal Fishing of the West: Fishing for Salmon out of Depoe Bay, Oregon. Bay fishing for the Giant Chinooks in Tillamook Bay that weigh up to 55 or 60 pounds. (07385)
  - H&W39 Skiing the Andes of Chile: The cameras go south of the equator to Santiago, Chile, showing the cities and the great ski areas of the Chilean Andes with spectacular skiing by Chilean and American champions. (07386)
  - H&W40 Alaskan Moose Hunt: A special hunt for a world's record class moose for a museum ends in success and a breathtaking camera shot over the hunter's shoulder in slow motion. (07387)
  - H&W41 Sand Point Kamaloops: Fishing in northern Idaho in Pend Oreille Lake with Rainbow Trout caught up to 22.5 pounds. [no print] (07388)
  - H&W42 Tygh Valley Indian Rodeo: A spectacular bone-cracking all Indian rodeo featuring slow motion rodeo at its best. [no print] (07389)
  - H&W43 High Lake Trout Fishing: The cameras follow fly fisherman and bait casters through a chain of high lakes in the Washington and Oregon Cascade Mountains. [no print] (07390)
  - H&W44 Duck Hunting: Combination of duck hunting and dunk banding by the State Fish and Game Department of Oregon. [no print] (07391)
  - H&W45 Western Rattler Hunt: A comedy of errors hunting for rattlesnakes in the hills of central Washington to be placed in zoos. [no print] (07392)
  - H&W46 Chinook Salmon Fishing: In the Columbia and Willamette Rivers of Oregon and Washington, the cameras record the spring fishing season for the giant Chinooks. [no print] (07393)
  - H&W47 Wilderness Trout Fishing: The cameras go into the remote back country of British Columbia to fish for 3 pound trout from a lake never fished by a whiteman or Indian. [Nulki Lake, near Tannock Lake off Vanderhoof, BC] [no print] (07394)
  - H&W48 Wisconsin Snowmobile Derby: A spectacular snowmobile weekend starring the versatile over-snow machines in a 42 mile race through rough country. Highlights two snowmobile jumpers who fly 45 feet through the air. [no print] (07395)
  - H&W49 Schweitzer Basin Story: A glorious ski weekend at Schweitzer Basin in Northern Idaho features skiing by Chuck Ferries of the Olympic Ski Coaches and Monty Steer who does a spectacular layout and flip on skis in midair covering 50 feet. [no print] (07396)
  - H&W50 Desert Bird Hunt: A shotgun hunt for quail, hungarians, and chukar in high desert country of Oregon. [no print] (07397)
  - H&W51 Winter at Crater Lake: A snowmobile trip around the rim of Crater Lake in deep winter and deep snow. Magnificent scenery with Crater Lake a deep blue and 15 feet of snow. [no print] (07398)
  - H&W52 Oregon Stage Coach Trails: Don Hobart's cameras follow the original stage coach routes of the 1900's in Oregon. A page of the Old West. (07399)
  - H&W Promos Segments likely taken from H&W episode 31 & 49 and WWP episodes 4 & 14 based on print labeled "Kayak, Flip School, Hang Glide" against show descriptions. [no print] (07400)
- Series B: Wild World of People, 1960-1971
  - WWP01 Skills - Pigs & Fords: Galundy Fiasco (galundy skiers), Slush Cup (ski race), Ski Dunning (snowmobile on sand dunes race). Pigs & Fords (Model T race while holding a pig) SS: YE OLD JOUSTING SOCIETY - mad dogs and Englishmen, and all that! A real medieval jousting tournament with full armor and real lances. Color, beautiful horses, pageantry and sore muscles. GALUNDY FIASOCO - comic slow motion crashes, spills and wipeouts as amateur galundy skiers attempt airborne acrobatics, sometimes with skis, sometimes without. SLUSH CUP - thick-skinned skiers frolic on a snow-capped but thawing glacier. With temperatures in the 90s, they snow ski down a slope in bathing suits and then attempt to water ski across a pool of freezing ice water. SKI DUNNING - expert snow mobilers try their machines on the sand dunes of the Pacific Coast, looking for a new vehicle for desert travel. PIGS & FORDS - a hilarious race among Model T Ford drivers who carry squealing squirming 50-pound pigs under one arm while they crank and drive a Ford around a racetrack. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 23 (07401)
  - WWP02 Dorys - Bathtubs: Dory Derby (dorymen in Pacific City, OR), Bath Tub Race (Vancouver Island to British Columbia) SS: SURVIVAL SCHOOL - living off the land, for real. A week in the mountains with a survival class; how and where to find food and how to prepare it. The class is taught by one of the top experts in the survival field. DORY DERBY - the pop of a parachute signals the start of a playday for the dorymen of Pacific City, Oregon. The youngsters race in the sand dunes while the men use their fishing and boating skills to play water games as only the dorymen can. BATH TUB RACE - hundreds of bathtubs in all shapes and sizes join in a 39-mile wild water race from Vancouver Island to the mainland of British Columbia, but most of the six horse power tubs sink long before the race moves into the open sea. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 17 (07402)
  - WWP03 Jeep - Santiam Drift: Four Wheel Rodeo (man-made racer track), Santaim Challenge (30 mile white water drift), Muzzle Loaders (white water float race), Chainsaw Artistry (timber statue). Santiam Challenge: Each spring in April the Challenge takes place the week before trout season opens. The rules are simple - cover 30 miles of wild, white, cold water in the swift Santiam River without drowning. Anything that floats is permissible. Rubber rafts, barn doors, innertubes, kayaks. There are no prizes; its all in fun and keeping dry seems to be the least of anybody's worries. SS: FOUR-WHEEL RODEO - water-filled ditches and steep slick hills compose the man-made track for a group of racers who spend more time in the mud than in the driver's seat. SANTIAM CHALLENGE - rafts, innertubes, anything that floats gets into this crowded fun-filled drift down 30 miles of rough white water. MUZZLE LOADERS - "mountain men" in buckskins and moccasins show off their shooting skills. CHAIN-SAW ARTISTRY - watch a wodden indian evolve from a cedar log. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 19 (07403)
  - WWP04 Motorcycles - Galundy - Kayaks: Motorcycles and Mud (ten lap muddy motor cross), Mt. Hood Festival (snow sculptures and galundy skiers), White Water Kayaks (national kayak race ay Wenatchee River). White Water Kayaks: An international kayak competition at Leavenworth, Washington in the raging Wenatchee River shows off the tiny 30 pound craft and the skill of the brave competitors that use them. The cameras go under water to follow the unlucky racers who spill in this wild river. Eskimo rolls and beautiful boat handling are necessary to compete in this tough race which is a preliminary to the Olympics competition. SS: JUNIOR RODEO - in White Swan, Washington, the youngster set takes to the arena in their own rodeo that is almost as rough as the "grown-up" kind. MOTORCYCLES AND MUD - motorcycles of all sizes join in a zaney 10-lap motorcross in mud so deep, bikes (and sometimes drivers) nearly sink out of the picture. MT. HOOD FESTIVAL - a fun day on the slopes of Mt. Hood featuring bigger than life snow sculptures and the hilarious antics of ameteur galundy skiers. WHIT WATER KAYAKS - a national kayak race, Eskimo rolls are followed by underwater cameras, while slow motion film captures the skills needed to battle the churning rapids of the Winachee River in Washington. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 20 (07404)
  - WWP05 Sammamish Boat Race - Timber Carnival: Sammammish Slough Race (outboarders race across water), Albany Timber Carnival (logger games). Albany Timber Carnival: The tough games loggers used to play for fun have now become a test of skill and endurance. Speed climbing 100 feet straight up and then descend as fast as you can, throw a 3 pound ax and hit a target 20 feet away, and cut through a 24 inch log with a hand saw in what seems like seconds. The ladies get into the act in the log burling, which means staying on top of a floating spinning 10 inch log with spiked shoes, while your competitor tries to spill you into the water. All part of a loggers fun day at Albany, Oregon. SS: HILLS & SPILLS - some want to go up and other want to go down! The motorcyclists do their level best to climb a steep hill and innertube riders almost kill themselves going down. Slow motion spills galore. SAMMAMISH SLOUGH RACE - a quiet slough is transformed into churning white water as 100 outboarders race across water and land to the cheers of thousands who line the banks. ALBANY TIMBER CARNIVAL - the crazy game loggers play provide plenty of action, including 100-foot pole climbs, log rolling, axe throwing and chopper contests. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 18 (07405)
  - WWP06 Sheridan Trout - West Yellowstone Snowmobile: Tourists' Bonanza (trout in Sheridan Lake, BC), Weekend at West Yellowstone (snowmobile race at Yellowstone National Park). A. Tourist Bonanza: Sheridan Lake, British Columbia, for 3 pound trout. Banff National Park for scenery and wildlife. It’s all an in-depth look at the fabulous province of British Columbia, our neighbor to the north. B. Weekend at West Yellowstone: The small town of West Yellowstone, Montana, comes alive during the winter months and is known as the snowmobile capital of the world. Snowmobile enthusiasts gather for the races in March each year to cheer for their favorite competitors, and to watch speed races up to 127 mph. Tours are available to take into the beautiful Yellowstone Park still wrapped in winter mantel that time of year. SS: TREASURE HUNT - how to look for gold and treasure with a metal detector. GOLD AND GRIZZLYS - a trip to Alaska to pan gold with a real old timer who doesn't need a metal detector to find gold. TOURISTS' BONANZA - wandering fishermen strike out rich in British Columbia's Sheridan Lake where 3-pound trout is the rule rather than the exception. WEEKEND AT WEST YELLOWSTONE - thrilling snowmobile races at speeds up to 125 mph with the splendor of Yellowstone National Park close by. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 22 (07406)
  - WWP07 Tygh Valley Indian Rodeo: Tygh Valley Rodeo (Native American rodeo).Tygh Valley Rodeo: A special and different rodeo takes place each year in May at Tygh Valley, Oregon. What makes it different is the contestants and the stock. The riders are all Indians and the stock is rounded up off the 3 million acre Warm Springs Indian Reservation and they are real wild horses. The only time they are ever handled or rounded up is for this rodeo, which makes it one of the wildest in the west. SS: TYGH VALLEY RODEO - a spectacular bone-cracking all-Indian rodeo featuring slow motion action at its best. WINNEMUCCA DOG TRIALS - the top field-trial dogs of the nation show up at this tough Nevada Chukar trials. A DOG NAMED CAT - a dog named "Cat" kills rattlesnaes for fun; a weird dance of death in slow motion. NOTE: SEGMENTS ALSO USED IN EPISODE 24 (07407)